<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.7.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://albince.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://albince.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-11T02:50:17+05:30</updated><id>https://albince.com/</id><title type="html">Albince Paliakkara</title><subtitle>Tech, Life &amp; Everything</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Why Your Releases Needs to be Rolling &amp;amp; Boring?</title><link href="https://albince.com/rolling-boring-release" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why Your Releases Needs to be Rolling &amp; Boring?" /><published>2020-12-11T01:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-12-11T01:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://albince.com/rolling-boring-release</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://albince.com/rolling-boring-release">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR:&lt;/strong&gt; Add features incrementally to production. Make Releases a routine task so that it becomes boring.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are you excited about your next release?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Do you have &lt;strong&gt;No deploy Fridays&lt;/strong&gt;? Are you waiting for the client’s business closing hours for production deployment?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If something is keeping you on your toes for the next production release, you need to improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;keep-the-code-rolling&quot;&gt;Keep the Code Rolling&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The aim is to get the code to be on production deployment as soon as possible. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lead_time&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Time to production&lt;/a&gt; should be minimised at all cost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The agile method advocates keeping the tasks atomic. For this to work, the &lt;strong&gt;Definition of Done&lt;/strong&gt; should be clearly stated for each task.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If something is marked as done after the different phases of &lt;strong&gt;Automated testing, QA verification and Product Owner’s approval&lt;/strong&gt;, why should it be further delayed to production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that shouldn’t be accessible to the end user, can be hidden using &lt;a href=&quot;https://devops.com/5-best-practices-for-feature-flagging/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Feature Flags&lt;/a&gt;. With the page/component behind the feature flag, you get to test your task while on production. This task can be further re-iterated by issuing subsequent tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/stephen-radford-hLUTRzcVkqg-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Thing on Fire&quot; title=&quot;A cute kitten&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;minimise-the-risk-and-blast-radius&quot;&gt;Minimise the Risk and Blast Radius&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Things may and will go wrong sometimes. This is applicable even if your release is occurring every Month/Quater/Year. But with incremental changes being delivered, the Definition of Done should include the steps required in case things go sideways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This may include&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Automated Database Snapshots before deployment&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rollback scripts in case of a destructive upgrade&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://vwo.com/ab-testing/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A/B testing&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://kubernetes.io/docs/concepts/workloads/controllers/deployment/#strategy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Different update strategy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;assets/images/edan-cohen-iSIiW--ACDs-unsplash.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Calm Cat in Bed&quot; title=&quot;A cute kitten&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;boring-deployments&quot;&gt;Boring Deployments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keep the deployments as boring as you can. The chimes in Teams/Slack during the production release/deployment needs to be minimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a nightly job for production release may be a bit ambitious(Or is it &lt;strong&gt;:P&lt;/strong&gt;). But with a click of a button, the continuous deployment tool should deploy the new release to the production environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To ensure a sound release, you can check the current status and analytics using tools like &lt;a href=&quot;https://grafana.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Grafana&lt;/a&gt;. Also having a fine-tuned alert system, like &lt;a href=&quot;https://prometheus.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Prometheus&lt;/a&gt; is encouraged.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Keep Calm and Enjoy Life&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Albince Paliakkara</name></author><category term="tech" /><summary type="html">TL;DR: Add features incrementally to production. Make Releases a routine task so that it becomes boring.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Dad, Pandemic, Linux and Remote Classes</title><link href="https://albince.com/my-dad-pandemic-remote-classes-linux" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Dad, Pandemic, Linux and Remote Classes" /><published>2020-12-01T01:00:00+05:30</published><updated>2020-12-01T01:00:00+05:30</updated><id>https://albince.com/my-dad-pandemic-remote-classes-linux</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://albince.com/my-dad-pandemic-remote-classes-linux">&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;TL;DR:&lt;/strong&gt; My 59-year-old dad teaches online MBA classes, creates youtube videos from his Linux laptop with google meet, libreoffice, audacity and kdenlive&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;covid-19-pushes-the-limits&quot;&gt;COVID-19 Pushes the limits&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pandemic has changed many things for my Dad. He is 59 years old and teaches MBA students.
With the COVID-19 restrictions, he was forced to do his teaching lessons online. Being the tech enthusiast in the house, I was called in as the consultant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He had already been complaining that his Windows laptop is very slow and there may be a virus in it. So I did what every Linux evangelist does. Wiped his laptop, and made a clean Ubuntu install. With the chrome starting up and his old videos playing through VLC player he nodded OK, but was not happy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With another couple of clicks, a Zoom meeting was running and he could send the join invite to my brother for checking voice, video, and screen sharing capabilities. With a couple of “Hello, testing” exchanges he was happy and started his remote classes the next day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;switch-to-google-meet-and-screen-sharing&quot;&gt;Switch to Google Meet and screen sharing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few days of starting the remote classes, my dad got the news that the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.hindustantimes.com/india-news/zoom-app-is-not-safe-for-private-persons-entities-mha/story-eAM93lrayy2N7sK90JgBAK.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Zoom is not safe anymore&lt;/a&gt;. As usual, I was called in, but this already had an easy solution of switching to Google Meet. IMO this was a very pleasant change for him. He found the google meet to be much more accessible and designed for Chrome browser.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a couple of days, I found him sharing the screen and switching between LibreOffice Impress and his PDF notes. I wonder what his students were thinking when they saw the ubuntu desktop and unfamiliar applications. Maybe he is the cool teacher with a fancy desktop for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;video-creation--youtube-channel&quot;&gt;Video creation &amp;amp; Youtube channel&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;sub&gt;Check out a class created by him. Please note the video is in the Malayalam language.&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;560&quot; height=&quot;315&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/ocHTq8nmEVc&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allow=&quot;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He didn’t even bother me once for the entire video publishing process of this one. He recorded the audio, created the presentation, merged them as a video class, and published it to youtube all by himself. For the first video, I showed him a sample of how to&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Record the audio using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.audacityteam.org/&quot;&gt;Audacity&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create the presentation using &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.libreoffice.org/discover/impress/&quot;&gt;LibreOffice Impress&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Merge the audio and video using &lt;a href=&quot;https://kdenlive.org/en/&quot;&gt;Kdenlive&lt;/a&gt; and render it to youtube compatible video format&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Later he found out ways to do the re-recording and insert it at specific places where there were mistakes in the initial recording.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;some-interesting-takeaways&quot;&gt;Some interesting takeaways&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My Dad is not a total newbie in the world of computers. He has some previous experience with Windows and a bit of passion for basic programming. But this was his first-hand experience with Linux and the video publishing process. With some things set up and getting basic instruction from me, he was able to get things started. Now he is getting better every day with googling stuff and figuring out things himself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Linux is a daily driver and gets things done for him.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;epilogue&quot;&gt;Epilogue&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He just asked me about how IP addresses work in a Wi-Fi network and whether Google will see them as unique users/visits. I guess he is now into SEO optimizations and increasing the reach of his videos/channel&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Albince Paliakkara</name></author><category term="life" /><category term="tech" /><category term="linux" /><summary type="html">TL;DR: My 59-year-old dad teaches online MBA classes, creates youtube videos from his Linux laptop with google meet, libreoffice, audacity and kdenlive</summary></entry></feed>